so yesterday we were talking about what
somebody I think in the comments rightly
spoke of the the switch in relation
between I ate and I thou so when we were
looking at the eyeball and describing
the eyeball to the other person that we
were looking at and then we held our our
vision there and then switch from
looking at their eyeball to seeing them
and feeling that difference right as it
brings up this mystery
because it it highlights that way in
which what I think I was trying to get
at before about where the place from
which the genuine question of being
resides it being closer to our closer to
ourselves closer to us than ourselves in
that our eyeballs bring us the same you
could say sensations they see they're at
the same place yet what I see is
completely different when I see thou the
other and what I think that highlights
is this way in which that can be an
analogy or how how being how we're able
to perceive being given that we can't
perceive it through there's nothing
about the sense perception itself that
can say being to you right in other
words you can't reduce it down to that
something else that perception of being
what is that
so if we look at this sense of I thou
versus I it and in for those of you who
are familiar with Martin Buber you know
you'll recognize this but you know
essentially you could say that his
Boober would say that the being a human
being essentially is always being in
relation and we are either as he would I
think poetically put it kind of
theologically philosophically poetically
say it is that we're either in a
relationship with an an ayat or in an I
vow essentially we could say that when
you're in a relationship with an ayat
both the I and B it he it is a meet I
had a phone call that apparently I found
out phone calls block they stopped the
video so and I believe I was what I was
saying before the this it
rudely interrupted me is the person who
calls right isn't it and I'm an I in
relationship to it because in some level
it was a it was a means that got in the
way of my ends right therefore it's an
it and Berber would say that is the that
is the relation as he would put it as
the world of time and space right that
it's though it's the world in which we
function where where the sidewalk is a
means to the end of walking right the
chair is a meet is a means to sitting
and there's a certain I that that arises
with that and he always Boober makes a
real strong point that that I it in I
vow or spoken as one word in other words
there's no I out there that then comes
together with an it out there no they
arise together it's always an i it i
thou whereas a dow which is much more
difficult to put into language because
when we ran i've our relationship to
where that which the i that is with thou
is in boobers words is an end in itself
it's another way of saying that using
Paul Tillich's language in some sense
it's like as if we face that of ultimate
concern right that of deepest concern is
is like it's like looking the deepest
ultimate concern the end in itself
directly in its face
and
there's a way in which it's spoken is
one word and you really get this because
you just look at the times of deep deep
connections with other people that
you've had it starts to explain a little
bit why a simple conversation can change
your life or a relationship that you
have with somebody can radically
transform the way you experience the
entire universe both positive and
negatively so the sense of I though the
eye becomes through thou and the bow
becomes through I and Buber would say
that that is I thou doesn't tap into
time and space it makes sense right
because usually those conversations that
are just in those interactions that are
so radically life-changing are usually
have this character where time
disappears we go into these radically
deep flow States
and so
the thing about it is that you can
oftentimes people don't even recognize
that when they relate to another person
they oftentimes you relate to that other
person isn't it there's a means to your
own end like you like them as long as
they say what they want as long as they
don't call you when you're trying to
shoot a video right then it reveals like
actually no you're a means to my own end
or on a much more subtler level like I
can relate to the other as a means to my
own end of approval or acceptance or
narcissistic reflection there's all
kinds of ways in which we can subtly be
in an i it relationship with another
human being so when we in boobers pretty
you know and I think this is also
telling it's it's not that I though
doesn't have to be with the vow doesn't
necessarily have to be with another
person he probably also had moments with
sunsets with in a moments of beauty
where the world stops right even tragedy
when the tragic and the truest sense of
the word I think can be one of deep down
right
so the thing to get about this and and
and and this is this why boobers this
what this part of boobers work has
always spoken to me is because in some
way it starts to really articulate why I
been circling for 22 years right why
people have been doing this how it
spread all over the worlds like what
well what's going on right I think it's
something like this and what you can
notice and I think that the part of that
that's it so personally developmentally
rich and liberating and transforming is
that you can feel when you go from
relating to somebody or something as an
it you can feel that when you start to
shift just like you shifted from looking
at the eyeball to seeing them when you
make that shift and you they become thou
you that's there's a corollary I that
you become in relationship to that thou
there's a different I that arises with
the bow and often it's like those
moments when you're the I thou you it's
it's paradoxically you you in so many
ways just like a flow state you
disappear the eye disappears into the
blossoming of the valve
and when you take that same valve it's
like flowering beauty and then they say
that thing that triggers you in that
moment you're like oh they go right back
into an it they go from a blossoming
flower mystery unfolding a centralist
center realizing itself in your your eye
that becomes world through thou - in
that moment you're like them I hate
that they betrayed me whatever you know
they're no longer a mystery you know
exactly who they are and what they
should do and what they did wrong and I
mean it's this is what I'm saying is
like what we're talking about isn't
something deeply esoteric in the sense
that it's super abstract the stuff is
talking about the structure the
underlying being of human being were in
a way that it the structure and the
context of relations that grant the
integrity that allows us to be human
beings that makes us human
and there's something that's been
speaking to me like had some other like
a whisper about all this that has to do
with that I've been realizing as I'm
hearing this whisper and I want to I
think I want to start to articulate at
some point we could say to begin to put
skin on the ghost they articulate this
thing in the periphery which is there's
something about the world and were the
world of the world and its relationship
to the I thou I it that I it's on the
periphery and I wanna some points start
to our see if I can start to articulate
it a bit more